<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Launch Academy | John Keith]]></title>
  <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/launch-academy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-01T19:50:49-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Keith]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Week Three and Designing for Efficiency]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/06/01/week-three-and-designing-for-efficiency/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-01T19:31:07-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/06/01/week-three-and-designing-for-efficiency</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Week three of Launch Academy was a short one with the holiday on Monday, but we covered a lot of ground. It was the start of the second module in the curriculum and we dove headfirst into databases this week. The relation database we are using right now is Postgres, which has been a nice change from the static data storage in CSV files we were using in weeks one and two.</p>

<p>We also had a great speaker come this week &ndash; <a href="https://twitter.com/PDegenPortnoy">Peter Degen-Portnoy</a>. He gave us a brief introduction to object oriented design, which will be the focus of our work this week.</p>

<p>Outside of our core material last week, I spent time wresting with problems of efficiency. I found myself still mulling over mechanics from the 2048 code I wrote in week two, looking for ways to improve the efficiency of the logic used to find random empty spaces on the game board. I knew our initial way was not ideal &ndash; it determined random X and Y coordinates on the board and checked to see if that space was empty. Eventually, I ended up benchmarking three different ways of finding a random empty space in a matrix and I believe I found a reasonably efficient way to go about it. (It is the middle method of the three below, which gives consistently better results, often taking half the time of the other two).</p>

<p>My goal is to continue thinking along these lines this week &ndash; learning about how to incorporate object oriented design into our apps while keeping an eye out for writing efficient code.</p>

<p>``` ruby
test_board = [[&ldquo;2&rdquo;,&ldquo;4&rdquo;,&ldquo;4&rdquo;,&ldquo;2&rdquo;],</p>

<pre><code>          ["4","2","2"," "],
          ["2","2","8","2"],
          ["4","3","4","8"]]
</code></pre>

<p>def insertRandomly(board)
  two_or_four = rand.round == 0 ? 4 : 2
  insert_successful = false
  while !insert_successful</p>

<pre><code>random_position_one = rand(board.length)
random_position_two = rand(board.length)
if board[random_position_one][random_position_two] == " "
  board[random_position_one][random_position_two] = two_or_four.to_s
  insert_successful = true
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>def insertLessRandomly(board)
  two_or_four = rand.round == 0 ? 4 : 2
  random_direction = rand.round == 0 ? true : false
  insert_successful = false
  while !insert_successful</p>

<pre><code>random_position_one = rand(board.length)
empty_space = nil
empty_space = board[random_position_one].find_index do |item|
  item == " "
end
if empty_space != nil
  board[random_position_one][empty_space] = two_or_four.to_s
  insert_successful = true
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>def insertByIndex(board)
  two_or_four = rand.round == 0 ? 4 : 2
  empty_spaces = []
  board.each_with_index do |row, row_index|</p>

<pre><code>row.each_with_index do |column, col_index|
  empty_spaces &lt;&lt; [row_index, col_index] if column == " "
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
  select_empty = empty_spaces.sample
  board[select_empty[0]][select_empty[1]] = two_or_four
end
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Launch Academy Week 1 Reflections]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/05/16/launch-academy-week-1-reflections/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-16T20:41:21-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/05/16/launch-academy-week-1-reflections</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Summing up week one of Launch Academy is tough: it&rsquo;s been a whirlwind of information and challenges. Here&rsquo;s what I do know: I could not be more excited to be here and on my way to becoming a software developer.</p>

<p>This first week really affirmed my desire to become a developer. Coming into Launch Academy, I was unsure of what life would be like working in web development professionally &ndash; I knew I&rsquo;d enjoyed tinkering in the past, but I didn&rsquo;t know what would it be like to be writing software everyday. At the end of this first week, I feel confident that I&rsquo;m going to enjoy this new career tremendously.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s not to say this week was without it&rsquo;s travails. The Launch Academy instructors stressed from day one that software development is not just about code: great software is the product of strong communication. This is definitely been a big shift in thinking for me as up until now I&rsquo;ve essentially been flying solo when coding. It is certainly taken some adjustment and I feel one of the most important things I&rsquo;ve been working on this week is learning how to collaborate and develop solutions with other people.</p>

<p>On the technical side, the past five days been a huge boost for my abilities in Ruby. As we take on bigger and bigger problems, I&rsquo;m really enjoying figuring out how to design programs and implement them as concisely as possible. Towards the end of the week, after seeing it mentioned in one of our Ruby challenges, I started playing around with the Benchmark module and it has been very interesting to look at how different ways of performing operations can be more efficient than others. Here&rsquo;s some messing around with different methods of calculating the nth number in the Fibonacci sequence that I found interesting.</p>

<p>```ruby</p>

<p>require &lsquo;benchmark&rsquo;</p>

<p>time = Benchmark.realtime do
  def fibonacci(nth)</p>

<pre><code>array_o_fibs = []
if nth == 1 || nth == 2
  return 1
else
  array_o_fibs &lt;&lt; 1; array_o_fibs &lt;&lt; 1
  until array_o_fibs.length == nth
    array_o_fibs &lt;&lt; array_o_fibs[-1] + array_o_fibs[-2]
  end
end
array_o_fibs[-1]
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  fibonacci(100)
end</p>

<p>puts &ldquo;The time elapsed in milliseconds is #{time*1000} with the non-recursive fibonacci method.&rdquo;</p>

<p>time = Benchmark.realtime do</p>

<p>  def other_fibonacci(n)</p>

<pre><code>if n == 1 || n == 2
  1
else
  fibonacci(n - 1) + fibonacci(n - 2)
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  other_fibonacci(100)
end
puts &ldquo;The time elapsed in milliseconds is #{time*1000} with the recursive fibonacci method.&rdquo;
```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Final Prep for Launch Academy]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/04/30/final-prep-for-launch-academy/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-30T18:10:06-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/04/30/final-prep-for-launch-academy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last part of our Launch Academy prep work is a moment of reflection. I feel like I&rsquo;ve come quite far since I started the prework &ndash; especially in terms of my understanding of Git. The Git Immersion and <a href="http://pcottle.github.io/learnGitBranching/">Learn Git Branching</a> were hugely helpful for me. Being able to visualize what is going on with rebases and merges made all the difference. Sandi Metz&rsquo;s book is by far my favorite of the readings and certainly the one I have spent the most time pouring over. Starting to understand the OOP patterns presented in that book has been a big turning point for me when it comes to grasping how entire applications are written and maintained.</p>

<p>In addition to finishing out my prework, I&rsquo;ve been spending a good deal of time on a site a Launch Academy staffer recommended called <a href="http://www.codequizzes.com/">Code Quizzes</a> and this has been a great way to sharpen all the Ruby that I&rsquo;ve been absorbing. Here are a few of the awesome methods and tricks I&rsquo;ve encountered so far from the quiz questions.</p>

<p><em>Question:</em>
<em>a = [1, 2, 3] and b = [&ldquo;a&rdquo;, &ldquo;b&rdquo;, &ldquo;c&rdquo;].  Use these arrays to make [[1, &ldquo;a&rdquo;], [2, &ldquo;b&rdquo;], [3, &ldquo;c&rdquo;]]</em></p>

<p>I really like the #zip method this question introduces. The #zip method allows you to combine two or more arrays with ease. Here&rsquo;s an example of combining three arrays.</p>

<p>``` ruby
a = [&ldquo;a&rdquo;, &ldquo;b&rdquo;, &ldquo;c&rdquo;]
b = %w(1 2 3 4 5)
c = [&ldquo;zip&rdquo;, &ldquo;method&rdquo;]</p>

<p>a.zip(b, c)</p>

<h1>[[&ldquo;a&rdquo;, &ldquo;1&rdquo;, &ldquo;zip&rdquo;], [&ldquo;b&rdquo;, &ldquo;2&rdquo;, &ldquo;method&rdquo;], [&ldquo;c&rdquo;, &ldquo;3&rdquo;, nil]]</h1>

<p>Hash[a.zip(b)]</p>

<h1>{&ldquo;a&rdquo;=>&ldquo;1&rdquo;, &ldquo;b&rdquo;=>&ldquo;2&rdquo;, &ldquo;c&rdquo;=>&ldquo;3&rdquo;}</h1>

<p>```
You can see from the above that zip can be quite flexible and formidable, mashing together arrays or even forming hashes.</p>

<p>The #cycle method is another interesting array operation that came up in questions on Code Quizzes. With #cycle, you can perform a block for a specified amount of times. For example, if you had an array you can use #cycle to print out its contents in order any number of times.</p>

<p>``` ruby
a = [1, 2, 3, 4]</p>

<p>a.cycle(4) { |i| p i }
```</p>

<p>Inject is certainly a method I want to master: it is really amazing how you can pass in a method to inject and let it do the work for you, without having to write a complete block.</p>

<p><code>ruby
[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 42].inject(:+)
</code></p>

<p>One question that had me a tad <a href="http://www.gullahbible.com/e-GullahNT/Conc/44JHNGUL.htm">bumfumbled</a> involved passing a method as a block and it being considered a Proc.</p>

<p><em>Question:</em>
<em>arr = [&ldquo;a&rdquo;, &ldquo;b&rdquo;].  Capitalize each element of arr with a proc.</em></p>

<p>The answer given was <code>arr.map(&amp;:upcase)</code>, which I am assuming means that you can pass methods as blocks and with some voodoo they turn into Procs.</p>

<p>Further on, there was a great question that begged for a similar solution.</p>

<p><em>Question:</em>
<em>Use a one-liner to find the longest word in the array: arr = %w{what is the longest word in this arrrrrray}</em></p>

<p>The site proposed the method below.</p>

<p><code>ruby
arr.inject { |longest_word, word| word.length &gt; longest_word.length ? word : longest_word}
</code></p>

<p>I think, however, it could be put more succicently with <code>arr.sort_by(&amp;:length).last</code>.</p>

<p>The larger pattern that I&rsquo;m begining to see is that with Ruby there is always another way, or twenty, to solve a problem.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Launch Academy in a Nutshell]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/16/why-launch-academy-in-a-nutshell/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-16T14:53:05-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/16/why-launch-academy-in-a-nutshell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As another part of our pre-work for Launch Academy, we&rsquo;ve been asked to setup a blog. Luckily, I actually (miraculously) got this Octopress installation started back when I was applying to Launch. That said, I liked one of the writing prompts provided to us as part of this exercise &ndash; &ldquo;Three Reasons I Felt Launch Academy Was the Best Fit for Me&rdquo; &ndash; and I thought offering my three cents on why I&rsquo;m heading to Launch could be informative for anyone else looking to apply to development bootcamps.</p>

<p><strong>Student-centric approach to everything</strong></p>

<p>Above all else, Launch Academy feels very student-centered. From the moment you start looking at their webpage to your first conversations with their experience engineers, the immediate impression you receive is that Launch is completely dedicated to their mission of transforming students from all walks of life into software engineers. Now, I&rsquo;m sure many, many of the other bootcamps out there are equally fixated on this goal, but I felt that Launch Academy had the greatest commitment to their students of any of the programs I talked with.</p>

<p><strong>Excellent, comprehensive curriculum</strong></p>

<p>One of the parts of Launch Academy that I spent the most time dissecting before making my commitment to attend was the curriculum. I wanted to make sure that after Launch I would feel prepared to jump into the job market as a web developer. I can say from many conversations and emails with the Launch staff that I feel confident the program will provide the broad exposure and focus on fundamental skills to transform us into capable and confident web developers.</p>

<p><strong>Post-graduation assistance</strong></p>

<p>This may be part and parcel of Launch&rsquo;s commitment to their students, but the career assistance that Launch offers to its graduates was another huge reason that I decided on them over other bootcamps. While many other programs talk about their tuition breaks for taking a job through a partner company, I believe Launch is much more focused on helping you find a job where you will both succeed and be happy, rather than one that benefits their partnerships.</p>

<p>And of course, Boston! Having come back from Korea almost three years ago, I&rsquo;m ready for a new adventure and a radical change of scenery. While I will miss Columbia (weather-wise and otherwise), I cannot wait to come up to Boston in May.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
