<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Octopress | John Keith]]></title>
  <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-22T18:39:02-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Keith]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Image Hosting for a Heroku Octopress Site]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/04/image-hosting-for-a-heroku-octopress-site/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T17:44:27-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/04/image-hosting-for-a-heroku-octopress-site</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since Heroku only allows for 300 MB of storage for their free tier of hosting, it makes sense to store the images for an Octopress site in a separate location. Previously, I used Flickr for a few posts, but the process of uploading the files and hunting down the embed link was tiresome.</p>

<p>The better way, it seems, is to use Google Drive, despite the fact that Google doesn&rsquo;t provide an easy way to embed either. What makes using Google Drive much friendlier than Flickr, however, is a site called <a href="http://gdurl.com/%E2%80%8B">gdURL</a>.</p>

<p>With gdURL, all you need to do is share an image file on Google Drive, change the privacy settings to &ldquo;Anyone who has the link can view&rdquo;, then run the link Google Drive provides you through the gdURL service and you receive a tidy, bite-sized link for embedding your image.</p>

<p>For instance, I used gdURL in the following line to link to a picture of this site&rsquo;s new theme.</p>

<p><code>
![So Fresh and So Green](http://gdurl.com/i4Wr)​
</code></p>

<p><img src="http://gdurl.com/i4Wr" alt="So Fresh and So Green" />​</p>

<p>Quick, easy, and keeps the size of your Octopress repo down.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Look for the Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/02/new-theme/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-02T21:20:50-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/02/new-theme</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been meaning to build an Octopress theme since I put this site up back in January. To start with, this blog was using the <a href="https://github.com/lucaslew/whitespace">Whitespace theme</a>, which was a fantastic starting point, but I wanted to create something with a little more&hellip;color!</p>

<p>After reading Vladi&rsquo;s post about creating a theme called <a href="http://vladigleba.com/blog/2013/10/31/introducing-readify-a-new-octopress-theme-focused-on-readibility/">Readify</a>, I was inspired to take a shot at it.</p>

<p>To that end&hellip;here&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;ve got so far. The code is <a href="https://github.com/johnkeith/sofreshandsogreen">available here</a>, should you want to install it on your own Octopress! I reworked the Classc theme to include a few basic changes that hopefully will make it more readable and usable.</p>

<ul>
<li>Larger font and line heights</li>
<li>Fixed navbar that becomes unfixed on mobile devices</li>
<li>Green everywhere!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
