<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[John Keith]]></title>
  <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-16T00:52:20-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Keith]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dynamically Control Button Labels With a Helper Method]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/14/dynamically-control-button-labels-with-a-helper-method/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-14T19:20:08-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/14/dynamically-control-button-labels-with-a-helper-method</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Reader beware: I’m learning Rails right now. In no way, shape or form should this post or any posts here for at least the next month and a half be taken as gospel truth of how to do things right in Rails. They probably are way, way out in right field.</em></p>

<p>Okay, say you have a view and in that view you have a beautiful button. If you want to assign a name to that button dynamically, say based on the truthiness of some variable, here’s an easy way to do it. </p>

<p>Open up the _helper.rb file for your model. In your _helper file, write a method that will provide you two pieces of text, depending on a certain condition.</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">sign_up_btn</span>
  <span class="keyword">if</span> <span class="constant">User</span>.sign_up_allowed == <span class="predefined-constant">true</span>
    <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">Prevent new account creation</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
  <span class="keyword">else</span>
    <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">Allow new account creation</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
  <span class="keyword">end</span>
<span class="keyword">end</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>Or, if you want to be fancy, try this refactored-while-in-the-midst-of-blogging-version. </p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">sign_up_btn</span>
  <span class="constant">User</span>.sign_up_allowed ? <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">Prevent new account creation</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> : <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">Allow new account creation</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
<span class="keyword">end</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>Then, back over in your view file, add this bit to create the button and assign it a title based on the results of the method above. </p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">&lt;%=</span> button_to <span class="key">action</span>: <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">disallow_sign_up</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">do</span> <span class="inline-delimiter">%&gt;</span></span><span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">&lt;%=</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">#{</span>sign_up_btn<span class="inline-delimiter">}</span></span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="inline-delimiter">%&gt;</span></span><span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">&lt;%</span> <span class="keyword">end</span> <span class="inline-delimiter">%&gt;</span></span>
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>(Just so you get a fuller picture, here’s my disallow_sign_up method from my users_controller. I wrote it as a way for an admin to turn off access to the sign up page in the expense tracking app I’m working on.)</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">disallow_sign_up</span>
  <span class="constant">User</span>.sign_up_allowed ? <span class="constant">User</span>.sign_up_allowed = <span class="predefined-constant">false</span> : <span class="constant">User</span>.sign_up_allowed = <span class="predefined-constant">true</span>
  redirect_to users_index_path
<span class="keyword">end</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>I have a serious fixation on the ternary operator, if you haven’t noticed. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simple File Uploads to Rails With Dragonfly]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/11/simple-file-uploads-to-rails-with-dragonfly/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-11T17:42:53-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/11/simple-file-uploads-to-rails-with-dragonfly</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Gems are amazing. As a rookie developer, it is incredible to come into the Ruby/Rails community and discover the wealth of code that is available out there, packaged and ready to be used. I’d encountered and enjoyed open source software before, but it was not until I started writing code that I really came to appreciate what the concept means.</p>

<p>Take for instance file uploading with Rails. You can perform basic uploads using what Rails offers natively or you can choose from a multitude of gems (Paperclip, Carrierwave, Dragonfly, the <a href="https://www.ruby-toolbox.com/categories/rails_file_uploads">list goes on</a>) that add more advanced methods of uploading and storing files in your Rails app. </p>

<p>For the expense tracker I am currently working on, I selected <a href="https://github.com/markevans/dragonfly">Dragonfly</a>. I’ll admit, I tried Paperclip first and I was unable to make it function correctly. My lack of success with Paperclip, however, was only half the reason I ended up with Dragonfly. </p>

<p>As I was envisioning document uploads in my app, I wanted the document (a receipt or invoice of a purchase) to become part of the Expenses table that I had already set up with a multitude of fields. With Paperclip, as far as I understood from the tutorials provided, it seemed like the documents would be set up as a separate model in the database, then associated with my current Expenses model. I can see advantages to the Paperclip approach (making all the documents easily accessible in one section of the database), but I wanted keep the relationships in this app as simple as possible, if only for my own sanity.</p>

<p>The great part about Dragonfly is it makes adding a :document column to your current model incredibly easy. The instructions below were what I did to install and integrate Dragonfly to upload documents when creating a new record in my Expense model. </p>

<p>First, I added Dragonfly to my gemfile and ran bundler.</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>gem <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">dragonfly</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>, <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">~&gt;1.0.3</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>$ bundle install
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>Then, in my app/models/expense.rb, I added an accessor for my document.</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>dragonfly_accessor <span class="symbol">:document</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>Back at the command line, I setup a migration to add a document column to my expenses model. </p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>$ Rails generate migration AddDocumentToExpenses
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>Inside the migration document, I added two columns, one for the :document_uid and :document_name, per the <a href="http://markevans.github.io/dragonfly/">Dragonfly wiki</a>.</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="keyword">class</span> <span class="class">AddDocumentToExpenses</span> &lt; <span class="constant">ActiveRecord</span>::<span class="constant">Migration</span>
  <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">change</span>
    add_column <span class="symbol">:expenses</span>, <span class="symbol">:document_uid</span>, <span class="symbol">:string</span>
    add_column <span class="symbol">:expenses</span>, <span class="symbol">:document_name</span>, <span class="symbol">:string</span>
  <span class="keyword">end</span>
<span class="keyword">end</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>Then came migrating the database.</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>rake db:migrate
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>Next was altering my app/views/expenses/_form.html.erb to include a field for file uploads. </p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="tag">&lt;div</span> <span class="attribute-name">class</span>=<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">field</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span><span class="tag">&gt;</span>
    <span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">&lt;%=</span> f.label <span class="symbol">:document</span> <span class="inline-delimiter">%&gt;</span></span><span class="tag">&lt;br&gt;</span>
    <span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">&lt;%=</span> f.file_field <span class="symbol">:document</span> <span class="inline-delimiter">%&gt;</span></span>
<span class="tag">&lt;/div&gt;</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Then, inside my app/controllers/expenses_controller.rb, I added :document to the list of permitted parameters near the bottom. </p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">expense_params</span>
    params.require(<span class="symbol">:expense</span>).permit(<span class="symbol">:user_id</span>, <span class="symbol">:date</span>, <span class="symbol">:reseller</span>, <span class="symbol">:item_or_service</span>, <span class="symbol">:payment_form</span>, <span class="symbol">:charged_to</span>, <span class="symbol">:cost</span>, <span class="symbol">:amount_from_budget</span>, <span class="symbol">:notes</span>, <span class="symbol">:document</span>)
<span class="keyword">end</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>With the next step, I was unsure if this was the correct course to take. I was worried about my files being uploaded to the public folder, as I assumed anything in that area would be easily accessible from the outside. I created a directory in the root of my app called secure_storage, though I have no idea if that name is a complete misnomer. Then, I opened the config/initializers/dragonfly.rb and changed the default location for where files would be stored. Again, hopefully this will put them in a better location than the public directory, but I am not a hundred precent sure. </p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>datastore <span class="symbol">:file</span>,
  <span class="key">root_path</span>: <span class="constant">Rails</span>.root.join(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">secure_storage/system/dragonfly</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>, <span class="constant">Rails</span>.env),
  <span class="key">server_root</span>: <span class="constant">Rails</span>.root.join(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">secure_storage</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>)
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>Finally, I added a file link (with a condition to make sure it didn’t appear if no file was present with the record) on the app/views/expenses/show.html.erb. </p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">&lt;%</span> <span class="keyword">if</span> <span class="instance-variable">@expense</span>.document <span class="inline-delimiter">%&gt;</span></span>
<span class="tag">&lt;p&gt;</span>
  <span class="tag">&lt;strong&gt;</span>Document:<span class="tag">&lt;/strong&gt;</span>
  <span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">&lt;%=</span> link_to <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">File</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>, root_url.chop + <span class="instance-variable">@expense</span>.document.url <span class="inline-delimiter">%&gt;</span></span>
<span class="tag">&lt;/p&gt;</span>
<span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">&lt;%</span> <span class="keyword">end</span> <span class="inline-delimiter">%&gt;</span></span>
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>That, I believe, was all! You should now have a working file upload function, one that even lets you download the file too! If you try this and have trouble, let me know in the comments below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Evernote With David Allen's 'Getting Things Done' System]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/08/using-evernote-with-getting-things-done/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-08T13:05:43-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/08/using-evernote-with-getting-things-done</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been using Evernote for a long time now and it has proven to be a fantastic system for storing information. That said, turning it into a system I can use to <em>organize</em> my life has been a Sisyphean experience. Over the years, my Evernote account has undergone a series of shakeups as I’ve tried out different organizational schemes, but each new system of handling notes, websites, and articles has left me feeling no more put together. </p>

<p>Part of our pre-work for Launch Academy has been to read a series of “brain hacking” books to get us ready for the start of the program. After diving into David Allen’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Getting-Things-Done-Stress-Free-Productivity/dp/0142000280">Getting Things Done</a>, I think I may see a way to corral my ever-ballooning Evernote into a much more manageable and useful repository. </p>

<p>Currently, I open Evernote to a slew of notebook stacks and subnotebooks.</p>

<p><img src="http://gdurl.com/CL5X" alt="My current Evernote" /></p>

<p>While having many individual notebooks is a passable strategy, I’ve found that it becomes less and less useful the more notebooks you create. My count right now is over 50 and I think that might be 44 too many. </p>

<p>An overabundance of notebooks starts to cause problems when you try to send something Evernote from within an app (like a newsreader or through email), as it always becomes a question of how to categorize this piece of information. By default, my notes are routed into a folder I called _INCOMING. This has been a nice landing spot, but the vagueness of the name (or perhaps its linguistic proximity to “inbox”) has contributed to my lack of desire to sort through the massive flood of stuff that piles up in there.</p>

<p>In Allen’s book, he divides the organizational process into five stages: <strong>collect</strong>, <strong>process</strong>, <strong>organize</strong>, <strong>review</strong>, <strong>do</strong>. To reformat my Evernote to follow this system, I’m going to start by creating a _Processing folder and setting it as the default location for collecting everything that hits my Evernote. This will be the folder that I’ll take the time every other day to process the items from - to figure out “what they mean and what to do about them” (Allen). </p>

<p>From the processing folder, an item will have four places to go: into the NextSteps, Projects, Incubating, or Archives folder. </p>

<p>In the NextSteps folder will be all todo items, things that need to be done in the short term or short term actions that need to be taken in relation to longer term projects or goals. </p>

<p>In the Projects folder will reside all of the <em>active</em> ideas or projects that I’m working on at the moment. And, as in <strong>Getting Things Done</strong>, the term projects is defined in a different sense than we usually use, as “any desired result that requires more than one action step” (Allen).</p>

<p>The Incubating (I wanted to use a more active term than Allen’s “incubation”) folder will house the more lofty and long term items - app ideas, career goals, etc.</p>

<p>Lastly, in the Archives folder, I’m going to store everything that resides in my current notebooks. In other words, the Archives folder is essentially going to house everything that passes through my Evernote - it is the final destination of all information.</p>

<p>I think this is the key to any organizational system - there must be a logical, actionable flow of information through the system, including a final resting place where the inactive information may be stored and retrieved. </p>

<p>Since Evernote does such a great job with indexing and searching any and every piece of information inside your account, I feel that there is no need to employ the tagging feature, that it might only slow down the movement of information into and through the new system. I’m going to spend some time not using tagging and see how it goes. </p>

<p>Allen emphasizes the important of reviewing the items in your organizational system at least once a week. I would love if it was possible to create a recurring reminder in Evernote that would alert me when I should review the information I have in each of my actionable folders (NextSteps, Projects, and Incubating), but for now perhaps a weekly calendar alert will suffice. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build What You Use as a Way to Learn]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/06/build-what-you-use-when-learning/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-06T17:38:44-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/06/build-what-you-use-when-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I can’t remember where I read it, but recently I came across the advice that one of the best ways to practice programming is to recreate the type of applications you use everyday. No need to make them flashy, simply implement their core features in order to achieve the same results. </p>

<p>I decided to give it a try today and build a tiny todo app in Ruby. I wanted to write the app keeping in mind the directives from Sandi’s Metz’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Practical-Object-Oriented-Design-Ruby-Addison-Wesley/dp/0321721330">Practical Object-Oriented Design in Ruby</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Remember that a class should do the smallest possible useful thing. That
thing ought to be simple to describe. If the simplest description you can devise uses the
word “and,” the class likely has more than one responsibility.​” - Metz</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While it ended up that my app only had one class, I tried to follow in the spirit of the quote above by keeping my methods as focused as possible. I also tried to heed her advice to stave off design decisions for as long as possible - an interesting strategy that had me trying to store all completed and incomplete todos in the same file. I quickly realized, though, that this was an inefficient way of doing things, since my completed items list would (hopefully) be a far larger file than my active items list and there is no reason to load that large file every time the app is opened.</p>

<p>There is one little quirk that I can’t seem to shake: when you mark a todo as finished, the item is removed from the activelist.txt file, but is not added to the completelist.txt file until you close the program. I’m sure it has something to do with the file opening modes I selected, but I can’t figure out why I am able to modify and then view the modifications done to activelist.txt while in the app, but not do the same with completelist.txt.</p>

<p>In the end, this was a great way to get practice using the File and IO classes of Ruby and exploring their methods. Not to mention, I get a pretty nifty little command line todo list manager (which I’ll stick in Dropbox for easy access) out of it! </p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>require <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">rbconfig</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>

<span class="keyword">class</span> <span class="class">Todo</span>
    <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">clear_screen</span>
        host_os = <span class="constant">RbConfig</span>::<span class="constant">CONFIG</span>[<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">'</span><span class="content">host_os</span><span class="delimiter">'</span></span>]

        <span class="keyword">case</span> host_os
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">mswin|msys|mingw|cygwin|bccwin|wince|emc</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>
                system <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">cls</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="regexp"><span class="delimiter">/</span><span class="content">darwin|mac os|linux|solaris|bsd</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>
                puts <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="char">\e</span><span class="content">[H</span><span class="char">\e</span><span class="content">[2J</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
        <span class="keyword">end</span>
    <span class="keyword">end</span>

    <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">open_app</span>
        view_all
    <span class="keyword">end</span>

    <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">view_all</span>
        clear_screen

        list_read = read_active_list
        
        puts <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">------INCOMPLETE------</span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
        list_read.each <span class="keyword">do</span> |line|
            puts line
        <span class="keyword">end</span>
        puts <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="content">----------------------</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>

        choose_action
    <span class="keyword">end</span>

    <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">read_active_list</span>
        list = <span class="constant">File</span>.open(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">activelist.txt</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>,<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">a+</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>).readlines
    <span class="keyword">end</span>

    <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">choose_action</span>
        puts <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">%/</span><span class="content">
        What would you like to do with your list?
        1. Add a todo
        2. Mark complete
        3. View incomplete
        4. View completed
        5. Exit</span><span class="delimiter">/</span></span>

        choice = gets.chomp.downcase

        <span class="keyword">case</span> choice
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">1</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> input_todo
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">1.</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> input_todo
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">add</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> input_todo
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">add todo</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> input_todo
        
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">2</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> mark_done
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">2.</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> mark_done
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">mark</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> mark_done
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">mark done</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> mark_done

            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">3</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> view_incomplete
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">3.</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> view_incomplete
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">view incomplete</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> view_incomplete
            
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">4</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> view_complete
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">4.</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> view_complete
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">view completed</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> view_complete

            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">5</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> <span class="keyword">return</span>
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">5.</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> <span class="keyword">return</span>
            <span class="keyword">when</span> <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">exit</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> <span class="keyword">then</span> <span class="keyword">return</span>

            <span class="keyword">else</span>
                p <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">Not a valid choice</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
                choose_action
        <span class="keyword">end</span>
    <span class="keyword">end</span>

<span class="comment">#ask for todo</span>
    <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">input_todo</span>
        puts <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="content">Enter your new todo:</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
        todo = gets.chomp
        add_todo(todo)
        view_all
    <span class="keyword">end</span>

<span class="comment">#write method</span>
    <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">add_todo</span>(todo)
        <span class="constant">File</span>.open(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">activelist.txt</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>, <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">a</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>) { |f| f.write <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">#{</span>todo<span class="inline-delimiter">}</span></span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> }
    <span class="keyword">end</span>

<span class="comment">#mark done method</span>
    <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">mark_done</span>
        clear_screen

        list_read = <span class="constant">File</span>.open(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">activelist.txt</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>,<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">a+</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>).readlines

        puts <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">------INCOMPLETE------</span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
        list_read.each_with_index <span class="keyword">do</span> |line, index|
            puts <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">#{</span>index + <span class="integer">1</span><span class="inline-delimiter">}</span></span><span class="content">. </span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span> + line
        <span class="keyword">end</span>
        puts <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="content">----------------------</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>

        puts <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="content">Which todo do you want to mark complete? (Type the number or zero to cancel).</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
        
        choice = gets.chomp.to_i

        <span class="constant">File</span>.open(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">activelist.txt</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>, <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">w</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>) <span class="keyword">do</span> |f|
            list_read.each_with_index <span class="keyword">do</span> |line, index|
                <span class="keyword">if</span> (index + <span class="integer">1</span>) == choice 
                    add_to_complete_list line
                <span class="keyword">else</span>
                    f.write <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">#{</span>line<span class="inline-delimiter">}</span></span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
                <span class="keyword">end</span>
            <span class="keyword">end</span>
        <span class="keyword">end</span>

        view_all
    <span class="keyword">end</span>

    <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">add_to_complete_list</span> line
        <span class="constant">File</span>.open(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">completelist.txt</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>, <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">a</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>).write <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="inline"><span class="inline-delimiter">#{</span>line<span class="inline-delimiter">}</span></span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
    <span class="keyword">end</span>

    <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">view_complete</span>
        clear_screen

        complete_list = <span class="constant">File</span>.open(<span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">completelist.txt</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>, <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">a+</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>).readlines

        puts <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">------COMPLETED------</span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>
        complete_list.each <span class="keyword">do</span> |line|
            puts line
        <span class="keyword">end</span>
        puts <span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="char">\n</span><span class="content">---------------------</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>

        choose_action
    <span class="keyword">end</span>

    <span class="keyword">def</span> <span class="function">view_incomplete</span>
        view_all
    <span class="keyword">end</span>
<span class="keyword">end</span>

my_todo_list = <span class="constant">Todo</span>.new

my_todo_list.open_app
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Image Hosting for a Heroku Octopress Site]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/04/image-hosting-for-a-heroku-octopress-site/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-04T17:44:27-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/04/image-hosting-for-a-heroku-octopress-site</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since Heroku only allows for 300 MB of storage for their free tier of hosting, it makes sense to store the images for an Octopress site in a separate location. Previously, I used Flickr for a few posts, but the process of uploading the files and hunting down the embed link was tiresome. </p>

<p>The better way, it seems, is to use Google Drive, despite the fact that Google doesn’t provide an easy way to embed either. What makes using Google Drive much friendlier than Flickr, however, is a site called <a href="http://gdurl.com/​">gdURL</a>. </p>

<p>With gdURL, all you need to do is share an image file on Google Drive, change the privacy settings to “Anyone who has the link can view”, then run the link Google Drive provides you through the gdURL service and you receive a tidy, bite-sized link for embedding your image. </p>

<p>For instance, I used gdURL in the following line to link to a picture of this site’s new theme.</p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre>![So Fresh and So Green](http://gdurl.com/i4Wr)​
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p><img src="http://gdurl.com/i4Wr" alt="So Fresh and So Green" />​</p>

<p>Quick, easy, and keeps the size of your Octopress repo down.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Look for the Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/02/new-theme/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-02T21:20:50-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/03/02/new-theme</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been meaning to build an Octopress theme since I put this site up back in January. To start with, this blog was using the <a href="https://github.com/lucaslew/whitespace">Whitespace theme</a>, which was a fantastic starting point, but I wanted to create something with a little more…color! </p>

<p>After reading Vladi’s post about creating a theme called <a href="http://vladigleba.com/blog/2013/10/31/introducing-readify-a-new-octopress-theme-focused-on-readibility/">Readify</a>, I was inspired to take a shot at it. </p>

<p>To that end…here’s what I’ve got so far. The code is <a href="https://github.com/johnkeith/sofreshandsogreen">available here</a>, should you want to install it on your own Octopress! I reworked the Classc theme to include a few basic changes that hopefully will make it more readable and usable.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Larger font and line heights</li>
  <li>Fixed navbar that becomes unfixed on mobile devices</li>
  <li>Green everywhere!</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finding Middle Ground With Middleman]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/02/05/finding-middle-ground-with-middleman/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-05T19:24:45-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/02/05/finding-middle-ground-with-middleman</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a while, I’ve been wondering - where is the better way of building static sites? I’ve made a ton of stuff working off of Bootstrap templates and Wordpress themes, but I also really love creating sites without all the mess of those big frameworks. I want to hand code sites to keep learning about the presentational side of web development, but an environment like Rails is not ideal for such explorations. Even the much more manageable Sinatra is only a little better, as I feel like my focus when building something in Sinatra is split evenly between the front-end and back-end. </p>

<p>That said, after finding and playing with <a href="http://www.middlemanapp.com">Middleman</a>, I believe it provides the perfect way to focus on the front-end of things without sacrificing the power of HAML, SASS and the like. The LiveReload extension is also amazing - it is incredible how small efficiencies make all the differences when writing and testing out new ideas. </p>

<p>I was really thrilled when I managed to figure out how to insert Markdown files into a HAML template built in a Middleman project. </p>

<div><div class="CodeRay">
  <div class="code"><pre><span class="class">.main-contain</span>
  <span class="class">.pure-g-r</span>
    <span class="class">.pure-u-1-2</span>
      <span class="tag">%h1</span> Hello folks.
    <span class="class">.pure-u-1-2</span>
      <span class="tag">%p</span> What up?
<span class="comment">      :markdown</span><span class="comment">
        #{File.read(File.join(File.dirname(__FILE__), &quot;test.md&quot;))}</span>
</pre></div>
</div>
</div>

<p>The code is nothing special, but being able to read a file of Markdown text and insert it into my template was pretty exciting. I’m planning to use this trick to create a text-heavy site that keeps its content as separate from the presentation as possible by inserting all the large chunks of text as Markdown files into templates. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Awesome Way to Learn HAML]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/01/27/awesome-way-to-learn-haml/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-27T22:23:38-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/01/27/awesome-way-to-learn-haml</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been meaning to take some time and learn one of the HTML templating engines. One of the best parts about the <a href="http://www.codepen.com">Codepen</a> site is that it is a great place to practice with engines like HAML and Slim. (Not to mention, doing so gives me a chance to try installing the Codepen plugin here on my Octopress). </p>

<pre class="codepen" data-height="400" data-type="HAML" data-href="sEzqJ" data-user="johnkeith"><code> </code></pre>
<script async="" src="http://codepen.io:/assets/embed/ei.js"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Treehouse Trial]]></title>
    <link href="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/01/01/my-treehouse-trial/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-01T13:47:35-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://johnk.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/01/01/my-treehouse-trial</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With the wonderful break from school here at the holidays, I decided to join Treehouse and explore this popular learning platform (and maybe pick up a little Objective C and iOS while I’m at it!). I’m on day three of a two week trial and so far I’ve been impressed by the site and its fantastic array of offerings, despite my devotion to Codeacademy. That said, after completing Treehouse’s <a href="http://teamtreehouse.com/library/usability-foundations">Usability Foundations</a> course and dipping my toes into the iOS Development track, I certainly have run across a few areas that could use improvement. </p>

<p>Before diving into the usability issues I’ve experienced, let me say that I have really enjoyed Treehouse thus far. I was initially wary of the video-lecture style that defines the Treehouse delivery mechanism, but I think there is something to be said for adding the human element of an embodied teacher when learning to code. While the learn-by-watching method of Treehouse differs greatly from the Codeacademy approach (code, code, code!), I am currently enjoying it as I start trying to unpack the verbosity of Objective C. </p>

<p>On the other hand, I have experienced some quirky behaviors after the video segments are done and you start to do the Code Challenges and other quizzes. There is a noticeable delay (as in 7 to 10 seconds) in between when completing the final exercise in a coding exercise (receiving the message “Congrats! You completed the challenge!”) and when the dialogue box appears telling you how many points the completion earns. </p>

<p><img src="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/images/postimg/nsstringChallenge.png" /></p>

<p>I’ve noticed this delay only occurs the first time you are completing a Code Challenge, not if you go back and retake a challenge. That fact, however, brings up another problem: when you complete a challenge you have already completed, you are still presented with a dialogue box telling you points are being awarded! It is certainly a little confusing to receive the message that I have earned 6 points for completing the NSString challenge, but then not see any change in my overall score. </p>

<p>I think the fixes in these cases could be straightforward. Simply offer a loading indicator if the long delay between challenge completion and points awarding is unavoidable. Then, if retaking a challenge already completed, make sure the dialogue box at the end mentions that this challenge has already been passed and no new points will be awarded. </p>

<p>In terms of quizzes, there are a few pedagogical problems when you answer a question incorrectly. On the iPad app, the user is given little feedback when a question is answered incorrectly - all you get is a red box and an unhappy beep. The web interface offers an experience that is much the same (an incorrect answer garners a message of “Bummer! Unfortunately, that answer is incorrect.”). </p>

<p><img src="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/images/postimg/bummerAnswer.png" /></p>

<p>What I really find frustrating is not this method of handling incorrect answers - the quiz should not tell you the correct answer as you are taking it, in case you do not pass. The problem arises when you reach the end of a quiz, perhaps with one incorrect answer, and are awarded your points without having a chance to review the question you answered incorrectly. </p>

<p><img src="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/images/postimg/incorrectAnswerPassing.jpg" /></p>

<p>I have run into this scenario multiple times on the iOS track: I’ve missed a question that I would love to know the answer to, but I have to retake the entire quiz to attempt the question again. This is a highly inefficient setup for both the user and the system.</p>

<p>Again, I think this usability problem might have a simple fix. Perhaps, at the end of quizzes on the iPad and the web interface, add a button that says “Review incorrect answers” that allows the user to review the question(s) they missed. </p>

<p>Changing gears, I’ve also found that navigating to courses and tracks you are currently enrolled in is not the easiest, both on  the web and the iPad app. With the iPad app, one tap when you open the app brings up the dashboard and shows you what track you are working on, then one more tap takes you right into the section of the track you are on. </p>

<p><img src="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/images/postimg/dashboardiPad.jpg" /></p>

<p>That said, you still have to scroll down to the lecture or quiz you left off at, but this is a minor inconvenience. </p>

<p>When you login to the web interface, you are presented with a Dashboard page that shows the current track you are on and a button to resume your progress, as with the iPad app. </p>

<p><img src="http://johnk.herokuapp.com/images/postimg/dashboardWeb.png" /></p>

<p>What is lacking from both interfaces, however, is any indication of other courses a user might be currently working through. (For example, though I am on the iOS Development track, I have also been watching lectures and taking quizzes from Usability Foundations, Career Foundations, and Database Foundations). Neither on the Dashboard page nor on my profile page is there a link to any of the other courses from the Treehouse Library that I’m working to finish. Having to click or tap on Library and then navigate through multiple layers to find the course I have started is difficult and undoubtedly poor from a usability standpoint. </p>

<p>Perhaps what Treehouse could do is offer a more informative Dashboard page. In the Welcome Home section of the web interface, current courses could be listed alongside the current track, accompanied by resume buttons. The same holds true on the iPad app - under the In Progress section, the current courses could also be visible and tapable. </p>

<p>Treehouse is an awesome product and I’m excited about continuing to explore its many facets, but I do hope the Treehouse Team will tighten up some aspects of the experience. I believe the few small tweaks above could easily make Treehouse one of the best online learning platforms available for aspiring developers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
